(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and welcome
back to the English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine.
And today we've got an
upper intermediate level lesson.
- That's right, we're
gonna go and buy shoes.
- Okay, this is very
fun, I like buying shoes.
Although I have a hard time
finding shoes in my size sometimes,
but we're here talking
about men's shoes specifically.
- That's right, we've
actually decided to talk about
this topic buying shoes
separately between men
and women's shoes because
I think each type of shoe
has its own type of vocab and that
could be very useful for men or women.
- That's right, so let's take
a listen to today's dialogue
and we'll be back in a moment to talk more
about the specifics of men's shoe styles.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, I'm looking for a
pair of shoes for my son.
- Sure thing, here we are.
If you're looking for dress shoes,
we have several different
styles of Oxford for boys.
We also carry athletic shoes, hiking boots.
- Oh, Jacob, how about these sneakers?
- Mom, they've got Velcro.
- Well, then how about these?
What is this style called?
- They're tennis shoes.
They're very popular with
teens and young adults.
- Oh, mom, can I get these?
- What are those?
They're Chuck Taylor's, everyone has them.
- Can I please?
- I don't know, would
they go with your clothes?
- The backs are really
high and the way the
tongue just sticks up,
they're almost like a boot.
And the soul doesn't look like
it would have a very good grip.
- They're only $45 and they've
got cool for us and orange shoelaces.
- Mom, mom, okay, try them on.
- What size are your feet?
- He has a size nine.
- We'll try a size 43 on you
first and see how that fits.
- Oh, what?
- They come in European sizes.
He should be a size 43.
I'll be right back.
- All right, we're back.
So as you saw, we have a
lot of different shoe styles
and so we're gonna take a look
at these on language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- Okay, first up, we have a
very popular style of shoe.
This is called an athletic shoe.
- Okay, athletic shoe.
Now, I imagine that
athletes wear these shoes.
- Good guess Marco.
- So athletic athletes.
This is actually for sports in general.
So this is sports shoes, but in
English, we say athletic shoes.
- Okay, so it's not specifically
for any type of sport,
but they're just comfortable shoes
that you can do most sports in.
- Right, like running
shoes and basketball shoes
and soccer shoes, these
are all kinds of athletic shoes.
- Very good, okay.
So these types of athletic shoes, they're
usually, they're kind of low, right?
They don't have a lot of
support around the ankle.
- No, but they do have a
lot of support in the heel,
the bottom of your foot, 'cause you're
running, you need that extra support.
- Exactly.
- Now, on the opposite,
if you're going hiking,
if you're maybe trekking, then
you need a special type of shoe
that's gonna give more ankle support
and these are called hiking boots.
- Okay, hiking boots.
So like you were saying,
you get a lot of support
in your ankle, that's the back of
your foot and the area around your leg.
So these shoes tend to
come higher on your leg.
They're taller on your leg.
And they're usually pretty heavy.
- Yeah, yeah.
And I think they are
more weather resistant.
So if it rains or if it's wet,
the shoes will respond better.
- You're not gonna get wet feet.
- You're not here.
And so hiking boots.
And now we have another interesting word.
I've never really understood
it why they're called this way,
but we have sneakers.
- Sneakers.
- Okay, I love sneakers.
I always wear sneakers.
A very common brand that
you see with sneakers is puma.
Also Adidas.
- Right.
- So converse is another brand.
Sneakers are shoes that are not fancy.
They're not like leather or work
shoes, but they're also not athletic shoes
because you don't necessarily use
them when you're playing sports.
They're basically very simple
shoes for normal, daily stuff.
- Normal walking.
Young people wear them usually.
- Okay, sneakers.
Now, I never understood
why they're called sneakers
because I think if you
sneak maybe on someone,
I guess these shoes are
good for sneaking up.
- Perhaps, I don't know.
They're less noisy than other shoes.
- Yeah, that's right.
Okay, so we have sneakers.
And now another type of shoe
that can be a little bit confusing,
they're called tennis shoes.
- Okay, tennis shoes can be
considered a kind of sneaker.
Again, it's not the kind of shoe
that you would normally wear to work.
It's not leather, it's not a hiking boot.
They're low shoes, so
low ankles, generally.
And they have, they tie up, you know?
- Right, but you would
think that you use these
shoes to play tennis,
not necessarily, right?
I mean, you don't have to play tennis
or they're not specifically
designed to play tennis.
- Now, perhaps originally
they wore tennis shoes
for the game tennis, but
nowadays they're very, very common.
They're like sneakers.
- Right.
- That most young people wear
to school or to play around in.
- Okay, so they're kind of,
yeah, like you say, a sneaker.
And now moving on,
these might seem a little
bit strange, but we
call them Chuck Taylor's.
- Chuck Taylor's, well,
basically Chuck Taylor is a brand.
- Okay.
- Converse, Chuck Taylor's.
We also call them Chuck's.
And this is a style of shoe that
this brand made very famous.
They're very, very thin canvas shoes.
So the fabric is not leather, it's canvas,
and they come in bright
red or black or green.
And some of them are very low,
and some of them have an ankle,
a piece of the ankle that comes up.
- So it almost looks like
a boot to a certain extent,
but it's not like a hiking
boot, it's not very hard.
It doesn't support your ankle as
much as just the style is higher.
- It's exactly.
And so because these are
made of fabric, they're very thin,
they're very light, they're not
very good for hiking, for example.
- Right, so these are
called Chuck Taylor's.
They're very, very popular
with teenagers, right?
- That's right, teenagers all over
the world, where Chuck Taylor's.
And I think they're very old, this style,
these Chuck Taylor's, having
around for like 30 years.
- Yeah, I think since the 1960s or '70s.
- But they're still popular.
- Yeah, and they haven't changed.
- They haven't changed.
- Right, so these are
the five types or styles
of shoes that we're
gonna take a look at.
Why don't we move on now
to more specific of vocab related
to the parts of the shoe on
language takeaway part two?
- Language takeaway.
- Okay, so Jacob is talking to his mother.
And his mom wants to know,
hey, how about these sneakers?
What do you think?
And Jacob says, mom, they've got Velcro.
- Okay.
- So Marko, what's this
Velcro Jacob speaks of?
- Well, as you can see,
Velcro is capitalized, right?
And so that means this is a proper noun.
And it's actually a brand.
- Okay, it's like Chuck
Taylor's, like Chuck Taylor's.
So Velcro is supposed
kind of like a zipper, right?
I'm fastener.
But instead of zipping it up,
you just put two pieces of
cloth together and they stick.
- Okay, and when you pull them
apart, - They make that sound, yeah.
- They make a loud sound.
And so sometimes with baby
shoes or young children's shoes,
we don't want to tie them
because that's too hard.
So we have Velcro.
This is a kind of fabric, like
you said, it sticks together.
We don't have to spend
all this time tying things.
So you see Velcro on hats,
on gloves, on jackets, on shoes.
It's a very popular way to make things
close things or to keep things secure.
- In a very easy way, right?
You just push them together and that's it.
They're sealed.
- Exactly.
- So the next time you see it,
now you know that it's called Velcro.
I imagine in other languages
it's probably called the same thing.
- Well, it's the brand name.
- Yeah.
- So, okay.
And well, now moving on to the
parts of the shoe, we have the tongue.
- Okay, well, think about the
body part, the tongue, right?
When you look at your
tongue, it's straight and
it's flat and it kind of
curves at the bottom.
- Right.
- Well, on a shoe,
when you're putting your
shoe on, you know,
in the front of the shoe,
you can make it stuck,
you have to pull the tongue.
It's a piece of fabric or piece of the
shoe where the top of your foot is.
- Mm-hmm, very good.
So that's called the tongue.
Now, some shoes have a
very small tongue or a low one.
Another has a very high one.
Like for example, Chuck
Taylor, they have a big tongue.
- That's right, very long tongue.
And so the tongue is the part
that rests on top of your foot
and usually the shoe
laces are over the tongue.
- Exactly.
And now moving on to the bottom
part of the shoe, that's called the sole.
- Okay, S-O-L-E, sole.
This is a really important part of shoes.
I always look at the sole
before I buy a pair of shoes.
Because this is the part that you use the
most because you're walking on the ground.
- Right.
- So, for example, hiking
boots, they will have a very
high sole and they will
have kind of like a pattern
so that you don't slip if
you're walking on dirt, right?
- That's right, sometimes
rubber, a rubber sole.
But other times like Chuck
Taylor's also have a rubber sole
but it's very thin.
- It's very thin.
And some shoes, for
example, they have a plastic
sole maybe because they're
used for other purposes.
So they might be a little bit slippery
if you go on to a smooth surface.
- Exactly.
- So the sole, that's the
bottom part of the shoe.
And the last part of the shoe
that we're gonna take a look at
and probably the most
important are the shoe laces.
- Shoe laces.
So shoe laces are
basically long pieces of
string that you use to
tie your shoes closed
because you want your
shoes to be tight on your foot.
You don't want it to be too
loose otherwise it might fall off.
And Chuck Taylor's and some other shoes
are very famous for
having crazy colored laces
or for people using crazy
colored laces to tie them up.
- Right.
So that's the part they use
to tie or tighten the shoe with.
So on the opposite,
if a shoe doesn't have
shoe laces, it's probably
gonna have velcro.
- That's right, velcro or shoe laces.
Okay, so those are all the
words that we have for you today.
Why don't we go back and listen
to the dialogue for the last time.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, I'm looking for a
pair of shoes for my son.
- Sure thing, here we are.
If you're looking for dress shoes,
we have several different
styles of Oxford for boys.
We also carry athletic shoes, hiking boots.
- Oh, Jacob, how about these sneakers?
- Mom, they've got velcro.
- Well, then how about these?
What is this style called?
- They're tennis shoes.
They're very popular with
teens and young adults.
- Oh, mom, can I get these?
- What are those?
They're Chuck Taylor's, everyone has them.
- Can I please?
- I don't know, would
they go with your clothes?
The backs are really high
and the way the tongue
just sticks up, they're
almost like a boot.
And the soul doesn't look like
it would have a very good grip.
They're only $45.
And they've got cool for
us and orange shoelaces.
- Mom, mom, okay, try them on.
- What size are your feet?
- He has a size nine.
- We'll try a size 43 on you
first and see how that fits.
- Oh, what?
- They come in European sizes.
He should be a size 43.
I'll be right back.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so talking about shoes, you
say that you always take a look at the soul.
Why is this?
- Because I'm always afraid that
my shoes are gonna wear out.
And I don't buy shoes very often.
I love sneakers.
I love my pumas and I love flat shoes.
And so when you buy a
pair of shoes, you really like,
you don't wanna buy
another pair in six months.
You wanna get a pair that has a really good
soul so that will last for a long time.
- Right, right, yeah, that's true.
I think for me, yeah, that's probably
one of the most important parts is a soul.
As long as it's comfortable, because
some souls of some shoes can be very rigid.
So it's a little bit
uncomfortable to walk with.
And but I don't know,
I don't really have
that many pairs of
shoes if I think about it.
- Well, most people have
one fancy pair of shoes
for special occasions and
then a pair of work shoes
that are leather and then
maybe a couple pairs of
sneakers and some sandals,
sandals, so the summer.
So what you have sandals and you
have flip-flops, so are they the same?
- Well, sandals is
basically a kind of shoe.
It's an open shoe that
you wear in the summer.
Flip-flops are a kind of sandal.
So they usually have a V in the front
and that's where you put
your big toe in the second toe.
- Yeah, so we wear them in
the shower or at the beach.
They're usually made of plastic or
rubber so that you can get them wet,
but their sandals are
flip-flops are a kind of sandal.
- Yeah, very good.
It's very interesting how
many styles and types of shoes
and actually for men, I
think it's not that complicated
but when we get into women's shoes,
they mostly have a lot of different things.
- There are too many styles.
I can't keep track.
- All right, so that's all
the time we have for today
but we'll see you guys on the website
if you have any questions, any doubts.
Or if you just wanna chat with
us, we'll see you at EnglishPod.com.
- See you guys there.
- All right, bye. - Bye.
(upbeat music)